Under the cover of darkness,
在黑暗的笼罩下
the world lies hidden from view.
世界从视野中消失
Without light, I've no idea what lies beyond my immediate surroundings.
没有光，我根本无法知道我身边的环境有些啥
I'm closed in, enveloped on all sides
我被包裹起来了，被四周未知的事物
by the unknown.
笼罩起来了
For much of human history,
人类历史上的大部分时间
when the sun went down and the dark set in,
当太阳落下黑夜降临
we were at the mercy of the night.
我们面对黑暗无能为力
But over the centuries,
但几个世纪以来
we've developed our own sources of illumination.
我们已经发展出我们自己的照明光源
We've lit our homes, our streets, our cities,
我们点亮我们的房子，街道，城市
and doing so, we've banished the darkness into the shadows.
就这样，我们驱逐了黑暗
And just as we've used light to illuminate our world,
在用光来照亮我们的世界的同时
the more we've discovered about light's properties,
我们也发现了更多有关光的性质
the more of the Universe it's shown us.
光也向我们展现了宇宙的更多秘密
We've seen into the depths of space...
我们曾望向星空深处...
..and back to the beginning of time.
...回到时间开始的地方
But as we've looked deeper,
但当我们向更深处望去
we've come to realise how little we've seen
我们便认识到我们看到的是多么小
and that the cosmos's greatest mysteries
也意识到，宇宙的最大谜团
remain hidden in the dark.
依然隐藏于黑暗之中
Light and dark is essentially the story
本质上来说，光明与黑暗就是
of everything we know
关于我们宇宙的故事
and everything we don't know about our Universe.
包括我们所了解的和不了解的所有事情
光明与黑暗
光明
天马字幕组出品中文字幕
翻译：马天一  校对：旧语新思 马成长
华中农业大学《欣赏物理学》专用字幕
后期制作：旧语新思 马成长
And it all begins with light.
而这一切都始于光
It's such an integral part of the way we perceive the world,
光是我们认识世界的一种必不可少的方法
it's easy to take it for granted.
也很容易被看着是理所当然的
But for centuries, understanding what light really is
但几个世纪以来，理解光到底是什么
has been one of science's most enduring questions.
曾经是长时间没解决的科学问题之一
The first steps toward understanding the properties of light
在理解光的性质的道路上
were made in the third century BC
最初的几步是在公元前三世纪
by the renowned Greek mathematician Euclid.
由著名的希腊数学家欧几里德迈出的
He did it by thinking about something so obvious,
他从思考一件最明显的事情开始着手
most of us don't give it any thought at all.
我们大部分人都不会去想这件事
Placing the tiny chair very close to the camera
将一把很小的椅子近距离的放在摄像机前
produces a large image on the retina,
就会在屏幕上产生一个很大的图像
and because we're not used to seeing tiny chairs in everyday life,
但因为在日常生活中我们并不常见很小的椅子
our brains are tricked into thinking
我们的大脑便误以为
it's a normal-sized chair in the middle of the room.
它是一把放在房间中普通尺寸的椅子
The reason this illusion works at all
造成这种错觉发生的原因
is because, to judge distances,
是因为，在判断距离上
our brains rely on a simple fact -
我们的大脑依赖一个简单的基本事实-
the further away things are
物体离我们的视线越远
the smaller they appear to the eye.
它在我们的眼睛里就显得更小
And it was by focusing on exactly why
通过关注究竟为什么
distant objects could appear the same size
远处的物体可以和摆的很近的小尺寸的物体
as much smaller ones closer up.
显示出相同的尺寸
...that led Euclid to discover of one of light's most fundamental properties.
...这使得欧几里德发现了光的最基本的性质之一
Obviously the London Eye is much bigger than my fingers, I know that,
很明显，伦敦眼比我的手指要大得多，这我知道
and yet to me they look the same size.
但对我来说它们看起来一样大
So, how do we explain this?
那么，我们该如何解释这一现象呢？
Well, Euclid came up with an elegant solution.
嗯，欧几里德提出了一个很简单的解决方法
For my finger to appear at the top of the wheel,
从我的手指一直到摩天轮的顶端
my eye, my finger and the top of the wheel
我的眼睛，我的手指和摩天轮的顶端
must all lie on the same line.
一定都是位于同一条线上
But Euclid's insight didn't just explain the tricks of perspective,
但是欧几里德的洞察力并不仅限于解释这透视的技巧
it revealed a basic truth about light itself.
它揭示了关于光自身的一个基本事实
Euclid had discovered that light travels in straight lines
欧几里德发现光是沿着直线传播的
Realising how it travels
意识到它是如何传播的
marks the beginning of our scientific understanding of light.
标志着我们开始科学地理解光是什么
And it also meant that if we could divert it from its straight-line path,
这也意味着如果我们可以转变光的直线路径
we could change the way we see the world.
我们就可以改变我们看世界的方式
But that leap wouldn't happen for another 2,000 years.
但这一跨越在之后的2000年都没有实现
It was eventually made in Renaissance Italy
最终实现这一跨越的是，在意大利的文艺复兴时期
by one of the founding fathers of modern science.
由现代科学的奠基人之一实现的
In the summer of 1609,
1609年的夏天
Galileo Galilei made the short but fateful journey
伽利略·伽利莱完成了一个短途却改变命运的旅行
from his home in Padua to Venice,
从故乡帕多瓦省到威尼斯
capital of the Venetian Republic.
也就是威尼斯共和国的首都
Galileo had flame-red hair, a full beard,
伽利略有着火红的头发，大胡子
and was well-known for his love of fine wines and generous hospitality,
人们知道他很喜欢葡萄酒，慷慨好客
and also for his anti-establishment views.
也知道他反正统的观点
By this time, he'd also built up a reputation
在那个时候，作为一个自然哲学家和数学家
as a natural philosopher and mathematician
他的声望也很高
and he was regarded as a valuable asset to the Venetian Republic
人们认为他是威尼斯共和国的宝贵财富
But although, as a professor, he had a regular income,
虽然，作为一个教授，他有固定的收入
Galileo was never far from financial troubles.
伽利略却总是摆脱不了财务上的麻烦
When his father died in 1591,
当他的父亲在1591年去世时
Galileo, the eldest of four surviving siblings,
伽利略，作为家中幸存的兄弟姐妹里最年长的一个
became the head of the household
成为了家里的顶梁柱
and, effectively, took on responsibility for supporting his brother,
并实际上承担了供养自己弟弟的责任
a poor itinerant musician,
他弟弟是一个贫穷的流浪音乐家
and for paying his sisters' dowries.
也承担了他妹妹们的嫁妆费
By the time he came to Venice,
当他来到威尼斯的时候
he still owed a significant amount of money to his two brothers in law
他仍旧欠自己两个妹夫一大笔钱
and so was always on the lookout for a money-making scheme.
所以他一直在寻找一个能赚钱的项目
That summer,
那年夏天
Venice was abuzz with rumours of a device
威尼斯到处都在传说一种装置
that appeared to do the impossible...
它可以做那些看似不可能的事情...
..a Dutch spyglass
..那就是一种荷兰的间谍玻璃
that could bring distant objects closer.
可以拉近远处的物体
It was just opportunity Galileo was looking for.
这正是伽利略所寻找的机遇
Back in the 17th Century,
回到17世纪
the spyglass was cutting-edge technology
被称为间谍玻璃的小望远镜还属于尖端技术
and the details of how it worked were a closely-guarded secret.
而内部的运作细节则是被严守的秘密
All Galileo knew was that it consisted of two lenses arranged in a tube,
伽利略也只是知道它是由两个透镜放在镜筒里组成
and so when he developed his own, he kept it very secret, as well.
所以他在开发自己的望远镜时，他也把制作方法作为高度机密
But we do know from a shopping list
但我们从一份购物单上知道了
that he got his glass from the small island of Murano, out in the lagoon,
他在环礁湖外的慕拉诺的小岛上购置了镜片
and because no tools existed, he had to improvise,
又因为手头没有现存的工具，他不得不临时拼凑
for instance, buying an artillery ball
举个例子，买一个炮兵球
to grind the curved surfaces of the lenses.
去打磨透镜表面的曲面
It had been known since the first spectacles were produced,
众所周知第一副眼镜的生产
in the middle of the 13th century,
是在13世纪的中期
that glass had the strange property of bending light.
那时的人们发现了玻璃能弯曲光线的奇怪的性质
But unlike spectacles,
但与眼镜不同的是
the spyglass, an early telescope,
小型望远镜，早期的望远镜
required a combination of lenses
需要通过一个非常特殊的安放
in a very specific arrangement
来将镜头组合
This is how Galileo's telescope works.
这就是伽利略的望远镜工作原理
Rays of light come in from a distant object
光线从远处的物体上投射过来
so they're almost parallel where they meet his first lens.
所以当它们到达第一片透镜时几乎是平行的
This is the objective lens, and it's plano-convex,
这就是物镜，而且是平凸型的
which means it's flat on one side and curved on the other.
也就是说这个镜片一边是平面另一边是曲面
It's the sort of lens used to treat long-sightedness
这类的镜片过去常用于治疗远视眼
What it does is bend the rays of light towards each other
它的作用就是使光线弯折彼此聚拢
so that they would meet at a point.
这样就能让这些光汇聚在一点
But before this focal point,
但在这个焦点之前
Galileo places his second lens, the ocular lens, which is plano-concave,
伽利略放置了他的第二个镜片，目镜，一个平凹镜
and this bends the rays of light back out again
就使得被弯曲的光线再次还原
so they emerge parallel, where they enter the eye,
这样一来光线就能平行射出，进入我们的眼中
and then the eye's lens focuses them on the retina.
然后眼睛的晶状体将光线聚焦到视网膜上
Now the magnification of a telescope depends on the ratio
那么望远镜的放大倍数取决于
of the focal lengths of the two lenses -
两个镜片的焦距比
the distances F1 and F2.
就是距离F1和F2
The difficulty for Galileo
伽利略的困难
was grinding down the convex surface of his objective lens
是在磨薄他的物镜上
to make it as shallow as possible
将物镜尽可能地磨薄
in order to maximise the length F1,
为的是使F1的长度最大化
because the longer he could make that,
因为如果它可以做到这一点
the greater the magnification of his telescope.
他的望远镜就可以有更大的放大率
Produced in just a few weeks,
仅用了几周的时间
Galileo's telescope had a magnification of eight times
伽利略的望远镜就达到了8倍的放大倍率
and was far more powerful than the original spyglass.
而且威力远比那些原来的小望远镜要强大得多
All he needed to do now
他现在唯一要做的
was cash in on his new invention.
就是靠他的新发明赚钱
Ever the showman, on the 21st August, 1609,
作为一个爱出风头的人，在1609年8月21日
Galileo climbed one of the city s bell towers.
伽利略爬上了城市的钟塔
BELLS CHIME
【钟声】
LIFT MUZAK: "The Girl from Ipanema"
【电梯里的音乐】“来自伊帕内玛的女孩”
Obviously, he would've used the stairs!
当然啦，他当年走的是楼梯！
At the top, in front of an assembled group of Venetian noblemen and senators,
在塔顶，在一大群威尼斯贵族和参议员的面前
Galileo demonstrated his telescope.
伽利略向他们展示了他的望远镜
It was a sensation.
结果是轰动性的
Using it, the Venetians would be able to see approaching ships
用这个望远镜，威尼斯人可以看见正在靠近的船只
two hours earlier than with naked eye.
比肉眼看到的早2个小时
The military and economic advantage of knowing who was sailing over the horizon
能够提前知道谁正在驶向岸边，其军事和经济上的优势这一点
was lost on no-one watching that day.
引起了当天在场的所有人的注意
Three days later, as a grand gesture,
3天之后，作为一个一鸣惊人的人物
Galileo presented his telescope to the duke as a gift.
伽利略将自己的望远镜作为礼物敬献给了公爵
In return, he was guaranteed his job for life,
作为回报，他有了一个双薪的工作
at double his salary.
来养家糊口
With his finances now secure,
现今他的经济有了保障
Galileo went on to develop a more powerful telescope,
伽利略便继续开发威力更大的望远镜
and with it, use the ability to bend light
并通过望远镜，这一可弯曲光线的能力
to change our perspective on the cosmos.
来改变我们对宇宙的看法
This is the book Galileo published in 1610.
这是1610年伽利略出版的一本书
It's called "Sidereus Nuncius",
书名叫“Sidereus Nuncius”
which in Latin means "The Starry Messenger".
这拉丁文译过来就是“星际信使”
In it, he recorded his first observations of the night sky
书中，他记录了自己第一次观察夜晚的星空
the first anyone had ever made
这是第一次有人
using anything other than the naked eye.
使用肉眼以外的东西来观察星空
Today, it's hard to imagine
今天看来，很难想像
how anything contained in this little book was controversial,
这本书中所包含的内容怎么会有争议性
but you have to remember that when it was written,
但你要记得在写这本书的年代
the nature of heavens was thought to be knowable only to God
人们认为天空的属性只有上帝才能知道
and the Earth was considered to be at the centre of the Universe.
而地球则被认为是在宇宙的中心
These are his drawings of the moon.
这些是他画的月亮
Since ancient times, all heavenly bodies were thought to be perfect spheres,
自古以来，人们认为所有天堂上的东西都是完美的球体
but with his telescope, Galileo saw texture in the surface of the moon,
但是伽利略用他的望远镜，看见了月球表面的纹理
deep craters and mountains
深坑和高山
that, from the shadows they cast across the lunar surface,
从投影在月球表面的阴影推算
he estimated to be some six kilometres tall.
他估计它们大约有6千米高
As well as showing the heavens to be imperfect...
也证明了天堂是不完美的
..his telescope began to uncover their true extent,
他的望远镜开始揭开天堂的真相
revealing ten-times more stars
望远镜所看到的星星数目
than are visible to the naked eye.
十倍于肉眼所看到
And in the final chapters,
在书的最后几章中
Galileo reports the discovery of four stars
伽利略报告了他发现的四颗星星
that appeared to form a straight line
几乎连成一条直线
near the planet Jupiter.
紧挨着木星
His drawings show how their positions change from night to night.
他的图画显示出它们位置每晚的变化
Although they moved, they always did so along the same straight line,
虽然它们在移动，但是移动时总是沿着同一条直线
and from that, Galileo deduced that they had to be orbiting Jupiter.
由此，伽利略推断它们的轨道是绕着木星的
They weren't stars at all, they were moons.
它们并不是星星，它们相当于木星的月亮
Through his telescope,
通过他的望远镜
Galileo had seen evidence
伽利略找到了证据
that overturned the accepted dogma
推翻了广为接受的教条
that the Earth was the fulcrum
也就是，地球就是核心
about which everything in the Universe revolved.
宇宙万物都围绕着它运行
Seeing moons in orbit around Jupiter
想一想运行于木星的轨道上的那些卫星
meant that not everything went round the Earth.
这意味着并不是所有的东西都绕着地球运行
So, far from being the centre of the Universe,
就更不用说作为宇宙的中心了
the Earth was just another planet.
地球只是另一颗行星
The telescope had allowed Galileo
望远镜使得伽利略能够
to glimpse the true nature of the cosmos
瞥见宇宙的真实属性
and our place within it.
以及我们在其中的位置
But this way of manipulating light
但是这种操纵光的方法
had another powerful application,
有着另一个强大的应用
one that would allow us to see into another world.
那便是让我们能看到另一个世界
BELLS CHIME
【钟声】
In 17th-century London,
在17世纪的伦敦
one of the most prominent scientists of the age
这个世纪最杰出的科学家之一
was using lenses in a very different way.
正在用另一种方式使用透镜
Robert Hooke had taken the basic principle of the telescope
罗伯特·胡克在了解了望远镜的基本原理后
and used it to build a microscope.
便将它运用在制造显微镜上
Galileo uses the telescope to discover a new world in the heavens,
伽利略用望远镜发现了天空的新世界
and Hooke uses the microscope to discover a new world
而胡克则用显微镜发现了一个
in the very, very small.
非常非常小的新世界
But there's a difference, because what Galileo had presented
但这二者有一个不同之处，因为伽利略所展现的
was a world that was bigger and more plentiful,
是世界更为辽阔更为丰富的一面
but it was a world that people were at least vaguely familiar with
但那至少还是个能让人依稀感受得到的世界
because you can look up in the sky and see the stars,
因为你可以仰望天空看到群星
whereas the world that Hooke presented
然而胡克所展现的
was really something spectacular and new.
则是一种全新的壮观的世界
It was a world inside the tiniest particles of matter
这是在物质的最小粒子里
that no-one had ever imagined to be there before.
一个人们之前从未想过的世界
People didn't even realise
人们甚至没有意识到
that there was a microscopic world there to reveal.
这是由显微镜所展现出的世界
Hooke trained his microscope
胡克用他的显微镜
on a huge range of materials and living things.
观察了大量的物质和活的东西
But it was his drawings of the exquisite detail he saw in the bodies of insects
但正是他所画下的他所看到的昆虫身体的精致细节
that would become famous.
使得这些画变得非常有名
Up here, you can see a human flea, Pulex irritans, a very tiny creature,
这里，你可以看到一个跳蚤，人蚤，是一种极小的生物
and here we've got the plate from "Micrographia",
而这里我们有一个从“显微图谱”里弄过来的印图
which is a huge image of the flea that Hooke produced,
这是胡克所创造的巨大跳蚤的形状
and it's really something spectacular.
而且这也着实有许多壮观的东西
This would've folded out in the book, so it was really very large.
这图当时折叠在书中的，所以它真的是非常大
Some people said it was as big as a cat.
有些人说它跟猫差不多大
It's a work of art, really. I mean,
这是一个艺术品，真的，我的意思是说
there's so much intricate detail in there.
这幅画里有这么多错综复杂的细节
It is, and there was nothing like it before Hooke.
确实，而且在胡克之前并没有像这样的东西
They really were unprecedented
它们真的是史无前例的
and the shading and the quality of the images is just superb.
而且阴影和图像的质量也是超一流的
And it's accurate. I mean, it's... It is, it's absolutely accurate
并且也很精准，我的意思是说，是的，它确实很精准
I was looking yesterday at images of, er, photographs of the flea and, er, there's really -
我昨天刚好看了，跳蚤的照片，那真是
made with an electron microscope -
用电子显微镜所照的
and there's really nothing to chose between Hooke and, er,
而两者真的没有什么区别，胡克和
the current images.
电镜的图像
This is an image of the compound eye of a fly,
这是一幅苍蝇复眼的图片
which Hooke shows in amazing detail for the first time.
这是胡克第一次展示如此惊人的细节
This is an image of the foot of a fly.
这是一幅苍蝇的脚的图片
Hooke shows you the foot has little spikes in it
胡克向人们展示了这个脚有很小的刺凸在上面
that allow it to clasp into the pores on a surface.
这就使得它可以扣紧物体表面的空隙
This image looks less interesting, less intricate than the others
这张图片看起来没有之前的有趣，也没有之前的复杂
It doesn't look terribly interesting
它看起来并不非常有趣
but, actually, it's really quite a profound picture,
但是，事实上，它真的是一幅意义深远的图片
because what Hooke is looking at here is a very thin slice of cork,
因为这是胡克观察的一个很薄的软木塞的切片
which he cut with a penknife,
他用小刀切下来的
and he's looking at the little individual components that make it up.
并观察组成它的每一小部分
And he calls them pores, and then he calls them caverns,
他把他们称之为气孔，之后又把它们称之为洞穴
he calls them boxes and then he calls them cells,
再后来叫它们盒子，最后他称它们为细胞
and cell, of course, is the term that stuck.
细胞，是的，那个被广泛接受了的术语
These are the little constituent parts, not just of cork, but of all living things,
这只是其中的一小部分，不只是软木塞，还包括所有的生物
and so it's a profoundly important discovery
所以这是一个极其重要的发现
and a name that has become standard in biology.
而这一称呼也成为了生物学的标准
Using glass to bend light
使用玻璃弯曲光线
revealed our true place in the Universe...
揭示了我们在宇宙中的真正位置...
..and the intricate architecture of the microscopic world.
..和拥有复杂结构的微观世界
The more we looked,
我们看到的越多
the more we saw.
我知道的就越多
With each new insight into the nature of light
随着每一次深入了解新的光的本质
came a fresh understanding of the cosmos.
对宇宙的了解也会更进一步
And the next discovery
下一个发现
would take us far further...
将把我们带入更深的一层...
..and enable us to read the story of the stars.
..使我们能够理解星星的故事
And it began with something Hooke had glimpsed through his microscope.
而这一切都起源于胡克通过他的显微镜所瞥见的东西
This is Robert Hooke's book The Micrographia,
这是罗伯特·胡克著的《显微图谱》
published in 1664,
出版于1664年
350 years ago.
距今350年
It's full of...
书里充满了...
..his famous diagrams.
..他的著名的图形
Here's his picture of the flea.
这张是他的跳蚤图
It's incredible seeing it in its original form.
看到它的原始形态真是令人难以置信
It really is the size of a cat!
它的尺寸真的和猫有一拼！
These images really captured the public imagination and they made the book a sensation,
这些图片真的抓住了公众的想象力也使得这本书变的非常有亲合力
but for me, The Micrographia is about much more than that.
但对我而言，《显微图谱》带给我的不仅仅是这些
The chapter that interests me as a physicist
作为一个物理学家最吸引我的一章
is one that contains hardly any images at all.
是几乎不含图的一章
And it's this one here -
就是这里的这一章-
"Of the Colours observable
“从白云母和其他薄片样本"
"in Muscovy Glass, and other thin Bodies".
"可以观察到的颜色"
Here Hooke describes the iridescent patterns of rainbow colours
这里胡克描述了彩虹五彩斑斓的图案
he sees through his microscope
他通过他的显微镜发现
as light passes through thin materials,
当光穿过很薄的材料时
like soap bubbles and Muscovy-glass,
比如肥皂泡和白云母片
a silicate mineral that's made up of lots of thin layers.
一种有许多薄层的硅酸盐矿物组成的东西
At the time, it was thought that white light like sunlight, was pure,
那时，白光被认为是像太阳光一样的，是纯净的光，
that it came directly from God
它直接来自上帝
and so Hooke concluded that the colours he was seeing
于是胡克得出结论---他看到的颜色
must have somehow been added to the light,
一定是以某种方式被添加到光里去了
that they were effectively created
当光通过材料时
as the light passed through the materials.
那些颜色的的确确地出现了
But Hooke's theory about coloured light
但是胡克的关于色光理论
was about to be challenged by his greatest rival.
正要被他最有力的竞争对手所挑战
Isaac Newton is one of the world's most revered scientists...
艾萨克·牛顿是世界上最受人尊敬的科学家之一...
..best known for his theory of universal gravitation.
..最为人所熟知的是他的万有引力理论
And just like his laws of gravity,
正如他的引力定律一样
Newton's discoveries about the nature of light
发现光的本质
are among his most celebrated achievements.
也是牛顿最著名的成就
But the story of how that work began is much less familiar,
但至于牛顿是如何开始这项工作的，就鲜为人知了
And this time, there was no fruit involved.
而且这一次 ，再没什么水果砸在他的头上
This is Stourbridge Common,
这里是剑河下游的南岸
a sleepy riverside meadow on the banks of the River Cam.
一片沉寂在剑河堤岸的草场
But when Newton's visited in 1664, it would've been very different.
但1664年牛顿拜访这里时，情况则是大不一样
For over 700 years, every September this place would be transformed
700多年来,每年9月这个地方将会
into what was, at its height, the largest fair in Europe.
变成它的，最鼎盛时期的原貌----欧洲最大的展览会
For several weeks each year, people would descend on the common
每年的这几个星期，人们都会涌向这片地方
for an annual festival of commerce and debauchery.
为了这个一年一度的商业和狂欢的节日
DOGS BARK SHOUTING
【狗叫声】
SWORDS CLASH APPLAUSE
【剑的碰撞声和掌声】
This whole common would've been packed with make-shift stalls
这整片地方都挤满了临时的摊位
farming produce, brandy houses, goldsmiths, silk merchants.
农产品，白兰地酒坊，珠宝商金匠，丝绸商人
There'd have been slack-rope dancing, puppet shows, music,
这里也有长蛇缓舞，木偶剧表演，音乐表演
temptations of every kind,
各种各样的诱惑
packed into row upon row of wooden booths and tents.
挤在这一排排木亭和帐篷里
Stourbridge Fair was a place you could buy anything you could imagine,
剑河下游的展览会是一个你可以买到你所想的任何东西的地方
but when Newton came here, it's said he bought just one thing -
但当牛顿来到这里时，据说他只买了一样东西-
a prism.
一个棱镜
He bought it because it performed the same magic
他买下了它是因为它展示了
Hooke had seen with his microscope.
胡克当年从显微镜看到的相同的戏法
Newton would later write that, using his new purchase,
牛顿后来写道，用他新买的小玩意
he would "try the celebrated phenomena of colours"...
他想要“试一下这种有名的色彩现象”...
..a rather understated introduction
..这是一个相当低调的引言
to work that would produce one of the most profound insights into the nature of light.
而这一工作会导致对光的本性的一种深刻认识
Newton devised an ingenious experiment
牛顿设计了一个独创性的实验
to discover precisely how these rainbow colours were produced
来精确地观察这些彩虹的颜色到底是怎么产生的
and to put Hooke's theory -
从而检验胡克的理论，这个理论认为
that they were created by the prism itself - to the test.
那些颜色是由棱镜本身产生的
This is Newton's own drawing of what he called his "Crucial Experiment".
这是牛顿自己画的实验图，他称之为“判决性实验”
In it, he arranged a prism so that sunlight -
在这里，他放置了一个棱镜
coming in from a small hole he'd made in the shutters of his bedroom window -
他在他自己床边的百叶窗上开了个洞，让阳光照射进来
passed through it and projected coloured light onto a screen.
阳光穿过棱镜，把色光投影在一个光屏上
Well, here's my light source
好，这是我的光源
and here's my prism
这是我的棱镜
which, if I arrange carefully,
如果我仔细地调整棱镜
I can get projected onto the back pillar.
我就可以把光投影到在后面的立柱上
Of course, none of this was new
当然，这没有什么新东西
People knew that prisms produced coloured light,
人们知道棱镜可以产生色光
but what Newton did next had never been done before.
但牛顿接下来要做的事情，之前就没有人做过
He first isolated one of the colours using a slit,
他先用一道缝隙孤立出一种颜色的光
so in this case,
所以这种情况下
the orange light.
只有橙色的光
He then passed that orange light through a second prism.
接着他又让橙色的光穿过第二个棱镜
Now, if Hooke was right,
这时，如果胡克是对的
then this prism should add the other colours to the orange
那么这个棱镜就会在这个橙色上再加上别的颜色
and reproduce the rainbow.
重新还原成彩虹
But all Newton saw was orange light.
但牛顿所看到的还是橙色
The prism wasn't adding any extra colour.
棱镜并没有添加额外的颜色
He concluded that the colours must be contained in the white light in the first place,
于是他断定这个光的颜色一定是包含最开始的白光中
that white light wasn't pure
那束白光是不纯的
and prisms don't add anything to it.
而棱镜并没有给那束光添加什么
Instead, they split it up into its constituent parts.
相反，棱镜把光分成了原来组成它的部分
Newton named the colours that make up white light
牛顿将这些组成白光的颜色命名为
"the spectrum",
“光谱”
and when this discovery was combined with the telescope
而当这一发现和望远镜结合在一起的时候
it would show us something remarkable.
它将向我们展示难以置信的东西
The spectrum would reveal
光谱将向我们准确揭示
precisely what it was we were looking at out in space
我们所仰望的星空的真实模样
This is a spectroscope.
这是一个分光仪
As sunlight comes in, it's broken up into its constituent colours
当太阳光照进来时，它就被分解为组成它的色光
and spread out much more finely than you'd get with a simple prism.
而且比你用简单的棱镜分散的更细致
Now, with this camera,
现在，通过这个摄像机
I should be able to show you what I can see.
我就能向你展示我所看到的
I'll just check that it's working.
我要检查它是否正常工作
Yes. OK.
好的，可以
When scientists first did this in the middle of the 19th century...
当科学家在19世纪中期第一次进行这种尝试...
I'm placing the spectroscope on top.
我把这个分光仪放在上面
..they saw something completely unexpected.
..他们看到了一个完全出乎意料的结果
You can see the colours of the spectrum as Newton would've seen them,
你可以看到彩色光谱，和牛顿当年看到的一样
but if you look more closely, you can see something else.
但如果你更靠近点看，你还能看到点别的东西
It's not continuous,
它不是连续的
it's broken up by lots of thin black lines.
它被许多黑线所打断
These are gaps in the spectrum.
这些光谱中有缝隙
It was soon realised that these gaps
不久人们就意识到
were due to atoms in the outer atmosphere of the sun
这些空隙是由于太阳的外层大气原子
absorbing certain wavelengths of light coming from its interior,
吸收来自太阳内部特定的波长的光形成的
and that they could be used
这样一来，人们就可以用它们
to work out the chemical composition of the sun.
来弄清楚组成太阳的化学成分了
Every element absorbs a unique pattern of wavelengths -
每一种元素只吸收特定模式的波长-
an optical fingerprint
一份光学指纹
that can be used to determine the chemicals
可以用来确定你在星空中看见的
that make up any bright object you can see in the sky.
任何发光物体的化学物质成分
And in Rome,
在罗马
one man was using this technique to study light
有一个人通过这个技术来研究
whose origins lay far beyond the sun.
那些来自其它星星上的光
Father Angelo Secchi was no ordinary priest.
安吉洛·西奇神父是一个不同寻常的牧师
He was charismatic and viewed as something of a heretic by his fellow Jesuits.
他魅力超凡却被他的耶稣会士视为异端
That's because he was also a professor of physics,
那是因为他同时也是一个物理教授
with a evangelical passion for astronomy.
对天文学具有福音派的热情
In 1852,
在1852年
Secchi was appointed Director of the Vatican Observatory.
西奇被任命为梵蒂冈天文台主任
Within a year, he'd built a new observatory
在一年之内，他在圣伊格纳斯教堂的屋顶
on the roof of St Ignatius Church, in the heart of the city.
建了一座新天文台，就在城市的心脏地区
At the time, most astronomers were interested in mapping the positions of the stars
在那时，许多的天文学家都热衷于绘制星星的位置
and charting their motions across the heavens.
并且在描绘它们在天空中的运动轨迹
But Secchi was different.
但西奇与众不同
He wanted to know what they actually were.
他想知道它们究竟是什么
So from his vantage point, high above the streets of the Eternal City,
就这样，在这个制高点，高于罗马城街道的地方
he began to meticulously analyse their light.
他开始一丝不苟地分析它们发出来的光
Fitting a spectroscope to the observatory's telescope
天文台的望远镜上加装了一个分光仪
Father Secchi laboriously recorded the spectra
西奇神父辛苦地记录了
of more than 4,000 stars.
超过4000颗星星的光谱
This is Secchi's book "Le Stelle", The Stars,
这是西奇著的书“Le Stelle”，星星
which he published in 1877.
他在1877年出版了这本书
And flicking through it,
翻看这本书时
you can see many of the observations that he made.
你可以看见他做的许多观测
This one in particular is interesting.
这一篇格外有意思
It shows some of the spectra he recorded.
它显示了他记录的光谱
The top one here is from the sun,
上面的一条是来自太阳的
but the second one is starlight
这第二条则是星星的光谱
It's from Sirius A, the Dog Star,
来自天狼星A，大犬座主星
which is the brightest star in the night sky.
是夜空中最亮的一颗恒星
It's 8.6 light years from Earth
距离地球8.6光年
and over 20 times as luminous as the sun.
发出的光是太阳的20倍之多
You can see from its spectrum this clear sequence of bands,
你可以从它的光谱中看到这些排列清楚的条带
which is the signature of hydrogen,
这是氢元素的特有标志
because it's a relatively young star.
因为它相对来说还是一颗年轻的恒星
The Universe's hottest, brightest stars
宇宙中那些最热的，最亮的星
have spectra rich in the two lightest elements -
光谱中都富含有两种明亮的元素
hydrogen and helium.
氢元素和氦元素
But as they age, they cool,
但随着年龄的增长，它们会变冷
and their spectra reveal the presence of many heavier elements.
它们的光谱也显示，出现了许多较重的元素
This third one is from the star Betelgeuse,
这第三条是来自恒星参宿四的
which is a red supergiant.
它是一颗红巨星
It's near the end of its life
它的生命已经快走到了的尽头
and so you can see from the many bands here
因此你可以看到这有许多条带
that it's composed of lots of different elements.
那是由许多不同的元素组成的
What's remarkable about this image is that,
这些图片是多么的引人注目
I mean, it really is one of the key moments in the history of astronomy,
我的意思是说，这真是天文学史上的最关键的时刻之一
that we can learn so much about what distant stars are made of
我们可以只通过检测远处的星所射来的光
just by examining their light.
就可以知道它的组成
But because Secchi had catalogued the spectra of so many stars of different ages,
但正因为西奇把这么多不同年龄的星分门别类
his observations led to something even more profound -
他的观测导致了更深刻的事情-
that by analysing starlight,
通过分析星光
we can determine the stars' life cycles...
我们可以确定恒星的生命周期...
..when they were born...
..它们何时出生...
..and when they'll die.
..它们何时又将衰亡
Understanding the spectrum
理解光谱
had allowed us to read the story of the stars.
让我们可以读到恒星的故事
It's quite incredible to think
想起来都让人难以置信
that what began as a simple experiment in a darkened room
始于黑屋子里的一个简单实验
could reveal so much about the Universe,
可以揭示出如此之多有关宇宙的事情
that the scant light from those tiny points in the night sky
那些来自夜晚天空中极小亮点的微光
could contain within it the epic drama of the heavens.
其中居然包含了太空的史诗剧
But that wasn't all the spectrum could tell us.
但光谱能够告诉我们的不光只这些
Today,We know that it's made up of light of many different wavelengths,
如今，我们知道光谱是由不同波长的光组成的
and that those wavelengths extend way beyond the range we can see
并且那些波长远远超出了我们人眼的可见范围
The spectrum, from the longest wavelengths used in radio communications,
光谱中，从无线电通讯中使用的最长的波长
to the very shortest wavelength gamma rays,
到最短的波长，伽马射线
covers a range of 30 orders of magnitude.
涵盖了30个数量级的范围
The longest are 1-followed-by-30-zeros
最长波长比最短波长要
bigger than the shortest.
大1后面跟30个0倍
That's the same as a spread in range of weights
这个数量级跨度用重量来衡量
from that of a single grain of sand
就好比从一粒沙子
to the weight of all the water in all the oceans on the planet.
到地球上所有海水的重量的跨度
And within that vast spread,
在这个巨大的数量级范围中
visible light - the frequencies we can see -
可见光-我们可以看见的频率-
covers a factor of just two.
最大波长只是最小波长的两倍
That's the same as the difference in weight
把这个拿到重量上来做比较
between this pebble and one twice its size.
就像这个卵石和它的大小的两倍
Are we all set, Doctor? Yes, I think so.
我们一切就绪了吗，博士？嗯，我想是的
And throughout the 20th century,
在整个20世纪里
opening our eyes to the full spectrum
面对全光谱，打开我们的眼界
revealed even more of the Universe.
揭示了更多有关宇宙的事情
If you had infrared eyes, here's how the sky would look.
如果你有一双红外眼，这便是你所看到的天空的样子
Infrared allowed us to see the Universe's coolest stars,
红外线让我们可以看见宇宙中最冷的星星
while radio telescopes,
而射电望远镜
sensitive to the longest wavelengths,
对长的波长十分灵敏
revealed a cosmos in turmoil...
揭示了骚动的宇宙...
It's the violent events that are picked up,
这是射电望远镜所捕获到的激烈事件
exploded stars and galaxies.
爆炸的恒星和星系
..and satellites have scoured the heavens
..人造卫星则翱翔在天际
for short-wavelength ultra violet.
捕捉短波长的紫外线
The OAO picks the ultra-violet light from hot stars,
轨道天文台(OAO)从热的恒星捕捉到了紫外光
which the atmosphere cuts off from ground telescopes.
因为大气层的阻挡，地面望远镜对此无能为力
And here's the very latest window - gamma rays -
而这里是最新的窗口 - 伽马射线 -
which are like very energetic x-rays.
非常像是高能的X射线
Seeing beyond the visible
能看见可见光之外的光
has allowed us to peer deep into the cosmos.
让我们能深入到宇宙的深处
I was cock-a-hoop about this.
我对这一成果十分骄傲
I, too, was wildly excited when I heard of this discovery.
我也是，当我猛然听到这个发现时
But the very fact that light had proved such a useful tool
但这一事实证明了光是一种
for exploring the Universe
探索宇宙非常有用的工具
depended on one of its most mysterious properties.
这取决于它自身最神秘的性质之一
Light behaves like a wave,
光的行为像波一样
but if it is a wave, what is it a wave in?
但如果它像波一样的话，那么这个波在什么里面？
Waves are carried across the ocean by the water.
波通过水来跨越海洋
The sound you can hear now is due to waves in the air.
你现在能听到声音是因为在空气中传播的波
In the vacuum of space, there is no air
在真空环境下的宇宙，没有空气
so there is no sound.
所以那里也没有声音
But the reason you can see me is because I'm lit by sunlight
但你可以看见我的原因则是因为我被阳光照亮
that has travelled 150 million kilometres
而阳光则旅行了1.5亿千米
through empty space.
穿越真空区
So, what is light,
那么，什么是光
and how can you have a wave in nothing?
你又是怎样得到一个不在任何物质中的波呢？
Answering that question would not only reveal what light is,
要回答这个问题不仅要解释光是什么
it would ultimately allow us to glimpse
它最终会让我们瞥见
the beginning of the Universe.
宇宙刚开始的模样
And the first part of the solution
而解决这问题的第一步
was a discovery that challenged our most basic assumptions
则是一个发现，这个发现挑战了我们
about how we see the world.
如何看世界的最基本假设
To our eyes, light appears to be everywhere
对我们的眼睛而言，光似乎无处不在
instantaneously.
又稍纵即逝
When I look out at the view, there seems to be no time lag,
当我看向这片风景时，似乎并没有什么时间延迟
no delay, while I wait for the light to reach me.
当我在等待光到达我时，光也没有耽搁
But towards the end of the 17th century,
但到了17世纪的末期
it was discovered that our senses are mistaken.
我们的这种感觉被发现是错误的
In 1672, the Danish astronomer Ole Romer arrived in Paris
1672年，丹麦天文学家奥利·罗默到达巴黎
to begin work at the city's observatory
开始了天文台的工作
and to continue his observations of the moons of Jupiter.
并继续观测木星的卫星
For more than a decade
历经十年多的时间
Giovanni Cassini, the observatory's director,
乔凡尼·卡西尼，该天文台的主任
had been documenting their orbits in minute detail.
已经编制好了它们每分钟的运行轨道
Jupiter's innermost moon Io
已知的木星最里面的卫星木卫一
is known to make a complete circuit around the gas giant
会环绕木星做一个周期性的运动
once every 1.77 Earth days `
每1.77天转一圈
that's every 42.5 hours.
也就相当于42.5个小时
Now, from Earth, we can see it disappear behind Jupiter
现在，从地球来看，我们可以看见它消失于木星的背后
and then re-emerge round the other side
并绕着它的轨道运行
as it travels around in its orbit.
又重新出现在了木星的另一端
But here in Paris in the 1660s,
但在17世纪60年代的巴黎
Giovanni Cassini had noticed
乔凡尼·卡西尼注意到
that the timing of these eclipses seemed to vary,
这些星食的时间似乎有所不同
sometimes sooner, sometimes later than expected.
有时候比预测的早，有时候则比预测的晚
Soon after he arrived in Paris
在他来巴黎不久后
Romer noticed that these fluctuations weren't happening at random.
罗默注意到这些波动不是随机发生的
When the Earth was closer to Jupiter,
当地球离木星近的时候
Io would be seen to disappear and re-emerge earlier.
所观测到的木卫一就会出现和消失的早一点
But as the year went by
但随着时间的流逝
and the Earth moved in its orbit around the sun
地球绕着太阳的公转轨道转动
so that it was further away from Jupiter,
使得地球远离了木星
then the eclipses appeared to happen later than expected.
这时日食的出现就比预期晚发生
Romer knew the moon always took the same time to travel around Jupiter.
罗默知道木卫一环绕木星一周的时间是固定的
His great insight was to realise that the variations were due to the fact
他惊人的洞察力促使他意识到这个变化是基于一个事实
that light itself takes time to travel through space.
那便是光穿过空间需要时间
Here's how it works...
这是它的运作原理...
The eclipses of Io appear later than expected
当地球离木星较远时
when the Earth is further from Jupiter,
木卫一日食的出现比预期的晚
because light takes a longer time to cover the greater distance,
因为光要更多的时间来走完这段路程
but they appear earlier when the Earth is closer
但当地球离近时它们又出现的早了
because light needs less time to reach the Earth.
因为光到达地球的时间减少了
Light isn't instantaneous.
光不是瞬时传播的
It travels at a finite speed.
它传播的速度是有限的
Today, we've not only measured light's speed with incredible accuracy,
如今，我们不仅以令人难以置信的精度测量了光速
we've seen it in motion.
我们还能够看到它的运动过程
This is a video made by scientists at MIT,
这段视频是由麻省理工学院的科学家拍摄的
using a camera designed to monitor extremely fast, chemical reactions.
用的摄像头是专门用来监控极快的化学反应的
It has a shutter speed of around a picosecond.
它的快门速度大约是一皮秒
That's a millionth of a millionth of a second `
也就是百万分之一秒的百万分之一
the time it takes light to travel just a third of a millimetre.
这个时间内光只能跑三分之一毫米
Now, look what happens when I press play.
现在，看看当我按下播放键时会发生什么
What you can see here is a pulse of laser light
你可以看到这是一个激光脉冲
moving through a water-filled bottle.
正穿过一个装满水的瓶子
To us, this would appear as the briefest of flashes,
对我们而言，这个过程稍纵即逝
but the camera reveals how the pulse travels through the bottle,
但摄像机却揭示了这个脉冲到底是如何穿过瓶子的
scattering and bouncing around as it hits the water molecules.
当脉冲击打水分子时，激光向周围散射和反弹
Light travels so fast -
光速真是快-
300,000 kilometres per second
每秒300000公里
that slowed down by the same amount,
以同样的程度放慢的话
a bullet would take an entire year
一颗子弹就要花整整一年的时间
to travel the length of the bottle.
来穿过这个瓶子的长度
It's one thing to know that light travels at a finite speed,
知道光速有上限是一回事
quite another to actually see it move.
确确实实看到它的运动又是另外一回事
The discovery of the speed of light was hugely significant.
发现光的速度有着重大意义
Not least because it proved crucial
不单单是因为它对揭示光到底是什么
to uncovering what light actually is.
是至关重要的
Born in the summer of 1831,
出生于1831年的夏天
James Clerk Maxwell would become one of the leading lights
詹姆斯·克拉克·麦克斯韦将成为19世纪物理学领域的
of 19th-century physics.
重要人物之一
GASPS APPLAUSE
【叹息声和掌声】
His work on electricity and magnetism
他在电磁学上的研究
was one of the greatest achievements of the age.
是那个时代最伟大的成就之一
This is Glenlair in south-west Scotland,
这里是苏格兰西南部的格伦莱尔
Maxwell's family home.
麦克斯韦的家乡
While he was growing up here, he developed an insatiable curiosity about the world around him,
当他在这里成长时，他就养成了一种对周边事物永不满足的好奇心
a desire to understand nature
一种理解自然界的渴望
that he would never lose.
这种渴望他从来没有失去过
The young Maxwell seems to have taken great delight
小麦克斯韦似乎很喜欢
in tormenting his parents and his nanny
折磨他的父母和他的保姆
by constantly asking them how things worked.
总是不断询问他们事物是怎样运作的
"What's the go o'that?" he'd say.
“那是个什么呀？”他问道
If anyone ventured an answer,
如果谁冒险给个答案的话
the young Maxwell would only be satisfied for a moment
小麦克斯只会满足一会儿
before asking them how they knew.
马上他就会问，他们是怎么知道的
Of course, none of this is particularly unusual for a child,
当然，对一个孩子来说，这没有什么特别不寻常的
but what sets Maxwell apart
但使得麦克斯韦与众不同的是
is that he was just 14 years old
年仅14岁的他
when he wrote his first scientific paper.
却写出了自己的第一篇科学论文
So young, that a friend of the family
因为太年轻，以至于他家的一个友人
had to present it to the Royal Society of Edinburgh on his behalf.
不得不代表他把这篇论文投到爱丁堡皇家学会
Maxwell was one of the greatest scientists who ever lived
麦克斯韦是史上最伟大的科学家之一
and it was here that he carried out his most important work.
而正是在这里，麦克斯韦开始了他最重要的工作
During the 1860s,
在19世纪60年代
Maxwell produced a virtuoso piece of mathematics
麦克斯韦导出了一个数学杰作
that showed electricity and magnetism
证明了电和磁
were different aspects of the same thing.
是同一个事情的不同方面
But his calculations would show something else.
但是他的计算显示了一些别的东西
Quite by accident, they would reveal the true nature of light.
很偶然,它们将揭示光的真正本性
These are Maxwell's four famous equations
这是麦克斯韦的四个著名方程
that describe the relationship between electric and magnetic fields.
它们描述了电场和磁场之间的关系
Curl of E
E的旋度
is minus dB by dt.
等于负的dB除以dt
E is the electric field, B is the magnetic field.
E表示电场，B表示磁场
Curl of B over mu nought...
B的旋度除以μ。... ...
div of E equals zero...
E的散度等于零... ...
equals epsilon nought... ...  equals nought.
... ...等于ε。... ...等于零
With a bit of algebra and manipulation,
通过一些代数运算和推理
these four equations can be combined to give one single equation.
这四个方程可以结合起来，给出一个单独的方程
So the way it's done is like this...
那么完成后的形式就像这样...
We take the curl of curl of E...
我们取E的旋度的旋度...
Hidden deep within his mathematics
隐藏在这数学公式下的
was something that even Maxwell didn't expect.
是连麦克斯韦都没有想到的东西
..epsilon nought... Grad E 2 div...
...ε。...E的梯度2...散度...
This second term is zero
这个第二项为零
and I'm left with Del squared of E...
然后我留下E的▽的平方...
..minus mu nought, epsilon nought
..负的μ。，ε。
D 2 E...
▽的平方E...
..by dt squared.
...除以dt的平方
This is the wave equation.
这就是波动方程
It tells us how an electromagnetic field
它告诉我们电磁场
travels through space.
是如何穿过空间的
Now, the important bit is this here -
那，最重要的就是这里-
mu nought, epsilon nought -
μ。，ε。 --
because it's related to the speed that the wave is travelling.
因为它与波传播的速度有关
In fact, the speed is given...
事实上，速度已经给出了...
..by one over the square root of mu nought epsilon nought.
..它等于1除以根号μ。乘以ε。
And if you work that out, you arrive at...
如果你把它计算出来，你就会得到...
..3 times 10 to the power 8 metres per second,
..3乘以10的8次方米每秒
or 300,000 kilometres per second -
或者3000000千米每秒-
the speed of light.
这就是光速
If electromagnetic waves moved at the speed of light,
如果电磁波以光速在运动
it could only mean one thing.
那只能说明一件事
Maxwell knew this had to be more than just a coincidence.
麦克斯韦知道这不仅仅是一个巧合
It meant that light itself had to be an electromagnetic wave.
这意味着光本身就是一种电磁波
The discovery that light is an electromagnetic wave
发现光是一种电磁波
explains one of its most puzzling properties.
解释了光的一个最令人困惑的属性
What Maxwell's equations show
麦克斯韦的方程告诉我们
is that light consists of electric and magnetic waves travelling through space.
光是由穿过空间的电磁波组成的
So light is simply electric and magnetic vibrations
所以光只是电和磁的振动
feeding off one another as they move.
当它们移动的时候就相互激发
And we now know that these electromagnetic waves have a remarkable property -
我们现在知道,这些电磁波有一个不平凡的属性
they don't need to be waves in anything,
它们不一定是在什么东西里面的波
they can travel through empty space.
它们可以穿过真空
I remember first learning about this when I was in my second year at university.
我还记得我第一次学到这个知识的时候是在大二
I was in lecture hall 33AC21 of the physics department at the University of Surrey,
在萨里大学物理系33AC21号演讲厅
the lecturer was Dr Chivers,
演讲者是奇弗斯博士
and I remember turning to my friend next to me
我还记得我曾求助于坐在我旁边的朋友
and remarking on how incredible I thought this was.
并且还评论说我认为这个属性太不可思议了
I could tell by his reaction that he thought I was a bit of a geek.
我还记得他当时的反应，觉得我有点怪怪的
But, actually, it is incredible that in just a few lines of algebra,
但，事实上，这确实令人难以置信
you can tell what light really is.
就这么几行公式居然能够说清楚光的实质
And the fact that light travels at a finite speed
而且光速有限的这个事实
has enabled us to do something else.
使得我们能够做一些别的事情
It allows us to look into the past.
使得我们能够看到过去
Looking at a mirror one metre away,
看向离你一米远的镜子
you see yourself as you were six nanoseconds ago.
你看见的是六纳秒前的自己
From Earth, the moon appears as it was one second ago
从地球看到的月亮，是一秒前的月亮
and the sun eight minutes in the past.
而太阳则是八分钟前的太阳
The further you look out in space, the further you look back in time.
你在宇宙中看的越远，你在时间上就看的更早
Light from the cosmos's most distant objects
光从宇宙中最远的物体传到地球
has taken billions of years to reach the Earth.
要花上几十亿年的功夫
But there's one source that has taken us so far back in time,
但是有一个波源把我们带到了更远的过去
we've reached the very limit of what can be seen with light.
我们到达了我们能看到的光的极限
In 1964, while converting a strange-looking horn antenna
1964年，在把一个怪模怪样的号角天线
designed for early satellite communications
从早期用于卫星通信的设计
to make astronomical observations...
改造成用来做天文观测...的时候
..Arno Penzias and Robert Wilson
..阿尔诺·彭齐亚斯和罗伯特·威尔森
began to pick up a mysterious signal they couldn't explain.
开始捕捉到一个他们无法解释的神秘信号
Here, we had purposely picked a portion of the spectrum,
这里，我们特意选择了光谱的一部分
a wavelength of seven centimetres,
一个7厘米的波长
where we expected nothing or almost nothing,
在这个波段，我们本指望没有或几乎没有信号
no radiation at all from the sky.
天空中完全没有这个波段的辐射
Instead, what happened is that we found radiation
但是，实际发生的状况是，我们发现
coming into our antenna from all directions.
来自各个方向的辐射都进入到我们的天线
It's just flooding in at us and, um,
那真是给我们泼了一碗冷水，嗯
clearly was orders of magnitude more than we expected from the galaxy.
显然这比我们从银河系的预测要多出几个数量级
At first, they dismissed it as noise,
起初，他们不予理会，认为这是噪音
something unwanted, generated by the antenna itself.
是一些没用的东西，是天线自己生成的
Now, we had some suspicion
现在，我们有了一些怀疑
because the throat of the antenna came into the cab and was a little bit warmer,
因为天线的咽喉处一直到操作室都比较暖和
and that was an attractive place for pigeons,
这对鸽子来说是个很有吸引力的地方
at least a pair of pigeons who liked to stay there, especially in the cold winter.
至少有一对鸽子喜欢停在那，特别是在寒冷的冬天
We didn't mind that because they flew away when we came,
我们并不用担心，因为当我们来时它们就会飞走
except that they had coated the surface with a white sticky material
除非它们把天线表面涂上了白色的粘性物质（鸟屎）
which might not only absorb radio waves but emit radio waves,
这可能不仅会吸收无线电波还会发射无线电波
which could be part or maybe all of our result.
这可能就是导致我们结果的部分或全部原因
With the antenna cleaned, and the pigeons -
在清理完天线，和鸽子后-
well, it didn't end well for the pigeons -
当然，对这些鸽子来说这样的结果不太好 -
Penzias and Wilson began searching for an astronomical explanation.
彭齐亚斯和威尔森开始寻找一个天文学的解释
But the signal wasn't coming from anything in our own galaxy.
但这个信号并不来自我们自己的星系
Nor did it appear to be coming from any other galaxy either.
同样也不是来自其他星系的
It seemed to be coming from everywhere.
它似乎来自每个地方
No matter when we looked, day or night, winter or summer,
不论是你身处何时，白天或黑夜，冬天或夏天
this background of radiation appeared everywhere in the sky.
这种背景辐射在天空中到处都是
It was not tied to our galaxy or any other known source of radio waves.
这与银河系或任何其他已知的无线电波源毫无关联
It was rather as if the whole Universe had been warmed up
这更像是整个宇宙一直被加热到
to a temperature about three degrees above absolute zero.
高于绝对零度三度的温度
And so we were left with the astonishing result
所以我们得到了惊人的结果
that this radiation was coming from somewhere
这种辐射是来自宇宙深处
in really deep cosmic space...
的某个地方...
...beyond any radio sources
...超越了任何我们所知道的
that any of us knew about or even dreamed existed.
或我们能想到的无线电来源
What they'd discovered was light so ancient,
他们发现的光是如此古老
it had been stretched out into microwaves
它的波长被拉伸到微波段
and cooled to just a few scant degrees above absolute zero,
冷的只比绝对零度高一点点
light that had been travelling to Earth
这些光一直在来到地球的途中
for almost the entire age of the Universe.
花了几乎整个宇宙年龄的时间
It hadn't come from a distant galaxy
它们不是来自遥远的星系
and it was far older than any star.
它们比任何恒星都要年长
Penzias and Wilson had discovered that the entire Universe was awash with light
彭齐亚斯和威尔森发现从宇宙大爆炸的余烬开始
from the embers of the Big Bang itself.
整个宇宙就充满着光
Called the Cosmic Microwave Background,
它被称为宇宙微波背景辐射
it was released when the Universe was just 370,000 years old
当宇宙还只有370000年的时候它被释放
and it gives us a snapshot of the cosmos in its infancy.
它呈现给了我们一张宇宙初始阶段的快拍
And here it is,
就是这张
the latest image of the Cosmic Microwave Background,
最新的宇宙微波背景的图像
taken by the Planck satellite and published in early 2013.
由普朗克卫星获得，并于2013年初发表
The different colours are fluctuations in temperature in the early Universe
不同的颜色表示的是在早期宇宙温度的波动
and the information they contain
它们所包含的信息
has proved priceless to cosmologists.
这对宇宙学家来说是无价的
The tiny variations in temperature are caused by matter clumping together
物质聚集在一起引起温度的微小变化
into what will eventually become stars and galaxies.
最终使它们成为了恒星和星系
But what's truly remarkable about this image
但这个图像 真正引人注目的
is that it's not just light from the early Universe,
并不仅仅只是这个来自早期宇宙的光
it's the very first light there ever was.
而是这个第一束光的初始模样
During the first era of its life,
从这些光诞生的最初时刻
the Universe was a fireball of hot dense plasma
宇宙是一个火球样的热的等离子体
that trapped light, preventing it from moving.
困住光，不让它移动
Then, as the cosmos cooled, the plasma condensed,
然后，当宇宙冷却后，等离子体凝聚
forming the first atoms...
形成第一批原子...
...and the first light,
...和第一束光
light that would become the Cosmic Microwave Background
这束光将成为宇宙微波背景
was released into the Universe
被释放到宇宙去
It's sort of hard to express what an astonishing achievement this is,
要想表达这个成就是有多么惊人是有点困难的
that from our small planet, orbiting an unremarkable star,
从我们自己的小行星，围绕着一个不起眼的恒星
we've reached out into the Universe
我们就能联系到宇宙
and seen as far as it's possible to see with light.
并通过光来尽我们所能地看得更远
The discovery of the Cosmic Microwave Background
宇宙微波背景的发现
appeared to complete our picture of the Universe,
似乎完成了我们的宇宙图像
the final chapter in our use of light
也是人类利用光来
to explore the cosmos.
探索宇宙的最后篇章
Understanding the nature of light has allowed us to illuminate our world.
理解光的本质让我们照亮了我们的世界
We've captured it from the depths of space and the beginning of time.
我们从空间深处和时间的开始处捕捉到了它
At the smallest scales, light has uncovered
在最小尺度上，光使得我们
the microscopic structure of living things,
发现了生物的微观结构
and at the largest,
而在最大尺度上
it's shown us our place in the cosmos
它向我们展示了我们在宇宙中所处的位置
and told us the story of the stars.
并告诉了我们关于恒星的故事
Virtually everything we know about the Universe,
实际上我们所知道的有关宇宙的一切
we know because it's been revealed by light.
我们知道，是因为它是被光照亮的
But just as it seemed light would lead us
但是，正当光似乎会引导我们
to a complete understanding of everything...
完整理解万物的时候...
...in the last 30 years,
...在最近30年
it's shown us something disturbing.
它向我们展示了令人头疼的东西
The vast majority of the cosmos can't be seen at all.
那便是绝大多数的宇宙根本看不见
Far from being a Universe of light,
远非一个光的宇宙
much of it is hidden in the dark.
它们大多数都隐藏在黑暗中
Next time,
下一期
how scientists came to the realisation
科学家是如何意识到
that more than 99 percent of the Universe
超过99%的宇宙
lies concealed in the shadows,
藏在阴影中
and the extraordinary quest
又是如何开展非凡的探索
to uncover what's out there in the dark.
来揭示隐藏在黑暗中的秘密
Whether you want to step into the light
无论你是想要深入的了解光
or explore the mysteries of the dark,
还是想要探索黑暗的神秘之处
let the Open University inspire you. Go to...
让英国开放大学 来启发你，请到
and follow links to The Open University.
并点击开放大学的链接
Subtitles by Red Bee Media Ltd
英文字幕由红蜜蜂媒体有限公司提供
请保留翻译人员相关信息，勿作商业之用
天马字幕组出品中文字幕
翻译：马天一  校对：旧语新思 马成长
华中农业大学《欣赏物理学》专用字幕
后期制作：旧语新思 马成长